בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Okay, today's דף daf is כ"ב chaf bet
and we're just a little behind at this stage. We pick up
on כ"ד עמוד ב', chaf dalet amud bet, about four lines, about
five lines before the lines get wide. תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: הכהו
על עינו. Hikah lo eino. So we're still dealing with the עבד
כנעני Eved Kenaani going free when an eye or tooth or a
thumb or toe is cut off or whatever. We'll see more about
that. Okay, so if you hit on his eye and it became
dim, או שינו ונדדה oh shino venadeda on his tooth and it
became loose so it didn't totally knock it out. אם יכול להשתמש
בהן עכשיו אינו יוצא לחרות. Im yachol lehishtamesh bahen achshav, eino yotzei
l'cheirut. If it's still usable, again I don't know what that means,
like he has 20% vision, how much vision does he have to
have? Okay, but if it's still usable, then he does not go
free. ואם לאו יוצא לחרות. Ve-im lav, yotzei l'cheirut. If not, he
does go free even though it has not been totally knocked out;
it's attached to the body. I mean we talk about hitting the
eye, we don't talk about gouging the eye out, so it's a
question about whether it's still usable, and that would be true about
the tooth as well.
Just a- I
understand, but that's presumably not what we're talking about, okay? So at
least that's how חז"ל Chazal understand it. It becomes functionally unusable. How
exactly, what exactly is the threshold is not clear. Okay, תניא אידך,
Tanya idach, we talk about another ברייתא. Baraita. הרי שהיתה עינו כהויה,
Harei shehayta eino kehuya, let's say his eyesight was already dim for
some- but you brought it from being dim to totally blind. שינו
ונדדה Shino venadeda
his tooth was loose, והפילה ve-hipilah and you knocked it out. So
אם יכול, im yachol, what's the measure of that? So it's like
the mirror image. אם יכול להשתמש בהן כבר, Im yachol lehishtamesh bahen
kevar, if the eye was still, he had some sight still, again
does that mean enough to read, does that mean what degree? But
if anyway it was still usable
beforehand, so then יוצא לחרות, yotzei l'cheirut, so then taking it from
being dim to blind you made it from usable to unusable, and
that's- he goes free. Same with the tooth. ואם לאו, Ve-im lav,
but if it was already unusable, אינו יוצא לחרות eino yotzei l'cheirut
he does not. וצריכא, Ve-tzricha, you need to tell me both of
these directions although they're similar points that we measure it by its
being usable. Nevertheless, you need to tell me both directions. דאי אשמעינן
הך קמייתא,
Di ashmi'enan
hach qamaita, had you just told me the first that going from
a whole eye to a not usable eye, but it still was,
you know, sight- but it still was, you know, was not totally
blind- so דאי אשמעינן הך קמייתא, di ashmi'enan hach qamaita, where was
I? משום דמעיקרא נהורא ברי והשתא נהורא כחישא, Mishum d'mei-iqara nehora bari
v'hashta nehora kakhisha, because there you actually did something quite substantial; you
made him from total good eyesight to, you know, marginal eyesight so
that-
and unusable actually, you know, not
even- he can no longer see even if I mean whatever he's
functionally blind. Okay, so that's a radical difference.
אבל הכא דמעיקרא נמי נהורא כחישא, Aval hacha d'mei-iqara nami nehora kakhisha,
but if you just started with barely visible, you know, barely usable
eye, you know, barely- like some minimal degree of eyesight so you
didn't start with full eyesight, אימא לא eima lo so even though
you brought it to blind I might think- I got it, I
got it- I might think that that's not significant enough for him
to go free. ואי אשמעינן הא Ve-iy ashmi'enan ha and if you
had just told me the latter case, so I would have said
משום דסמיא לגמרי mishum d'samya l'gamre because you brought it down to
zero, אבל הכא דלא סמיא לגמרי aval hacha d'lo samya l'gamre but
where you didn't bring it down to zero, when you brought it
just down to not usable but still not to zero, so אימא
לא eima lo maybe he wouldn't go free. צריכא, Tzericha, you need
to tell me both cases.
Okay. Can we not because I got-
I want to keep on moving. We're okay. תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan.
הרי שהיה רבו רופא, Harei shehayah rabeih rofe, let's say his master
was a- his owner
was a doctor and he said to him,
לכחול לו עינו וסמאה, lechkohl lo eino ve-simah, let's say his master
was a doctor and he said to him I need you to
apply some, you know, some ointment in my eye, that's what this
לכחול likchol is, it's some type of a powder or ointment that
was put in the eye, and accidentally he blinded him. So he
was trying to help him but accidentally he blinded him. לחתור לו
שינו, Lachator lo shino, he tried to, I don't know, like fill
a cavity or something, והפילה ve-hipilah and accidentally he knocked a tooth
out. So שיחק באדון ויצא לחרות, sicheiq b'adon v'yatzah l'cheirut, he laughs
in the master's face and he goes free לחרות. l'cheirut. Okay, so
it doesn't matter if he was trying to help, it matters that
the end result was he knocked out the eye. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer: ושחתה, V'shichatah, the verse says
that he destroys it, which describes not just the result but the
nature of the act and the intent of the act. עד שיתכוין
לשחתה, Ad she-yitkavein l'shachtah, it's only in an act that he's trying
to destroy. Now presumably that would also include an act of violence.
He smacks the slave in the, you know, in the face; he
wasn't trying to knock out the tooth but it was an intentional
act of violence done to the slave. But what it is excluding
is a case of trying to help the slave, something that is
therapeutic which accidentally then knocks out a tooth, that would not be
free- and הכהו כנגד...
hicahu keneged... you know... what? He has it before... he- הכהו כנגד
hicahu keneged but-
that's about whether it hit directly or not. This is about what
the- whether- what the intent was, what the nature of the act
was, was the act- violence act against the body of the slave
or was it a helping the slave that led to the result?
Okay. ורבנן האי ושחתה מאי עביד ליה? Verabbanan, hai v'shichatah mai avid
lei? So the Rabbis who don't require that... be an act of
violence, so they say even if you tried to help, what do
they do what's the intention of ושיחתה, veshichatah, which seems to describe
the nature of it as a destructive act? So מיבעי ליה לכדתניא,
mibaei lei lechidatanya, like we taught in the ברייתא. baraita. רבי אלעזר
אומר: Rabbi Elazar omer: הרי שהושיט ידו למעי שפחתו harei shehoshit yado
lemei shifchato וסימא עובר שבמעיה. vesima ubar shebime'eha.
Let's say, let's say your maidservant was giving birth and you're a
doctor and you were trying to help her give birth and you
stuck your hand inside, you know, for to try to take the
baby out, and in the process of trying to take the baby
out, you blinded the eye of the baby, okay, וסימא עובר שבמעיה.
vesima ubar shebime'eha.
Now that's already interesting that this baby could go out before he's
even born, right? That it has that independent status, right? That's the
whole question of עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo and at what
stage during childbirth is the baby considered independent or not? Anyway, but
let's—but we're assuming that the baby could in theory go free. Nevertheless,
פטור. patur. Why? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר קרא ושיחתה amar kra
veshichatah עד שיתכוון לשחתה. ad sheyitkaven leshachatah. So the phrase ושיחתה veshichatah
here is a little misleading because this is the רבנן Rabbanan that
are saying you don't have to do it as a destructive act,
but the difference here is that you're not doing—you're not even relating
to the eye itself, right? You're just trying to grab the עובר,
ubar, you're not seeing the eye, you're not even relating to the
eye at all. Now it is interesting, like let's say you're not
relating to the eye again, you smack the guy in the face
and it knocks out a tooth. I presumably you're not punching the
tooth, you punch him in the face and knock out a tooth,
right? So—so is that you're not מתכוון mitkaven to the tooth, you're
מתכוון mitkaven to the face? So it's not exactly clear what the
line is, but I guess, you know, something like that would sort
of be a type of a, you know, אינו מתכוון eino mitkaven
פסיק רישא psik reisha type of a thing, like you're hitting him
in that area of the face, that's intending the tooth. But you're
not even seeing the fetus, you're not even aware that you're anywhere
near the eye area of the fetus or anything of that nature.
That makes it a completely different
thing.
כנגד עינו ואינו רואה כנגד אזנו ואינו שומע, keneged eino ve'eino ro'eh
keneged ozno ve'eino shome'a, further up on top, אין עבד יוצא בהן
לחירות. ein eved yotzei bahen lecherut. You're saying then if you hit
him on the face not by the tooth he does go free?
How's that—isn't that...?
No, no, no, no. That issue was that you weren't even hitting
him around the face. רש״י Rashi says like you hit nearby on
the wall and there was another question about מבעית. mav'it. You don't
have to actually—I mean if you hit here, right, what? It's like
a חציצה chatsitzah between your—between your hand and the tooth? That's not
enough, right? If somebody, I mean, let's say, I don't know, let's
say somebody tries to protect himself and he put up his hand
against his eye and you banged his hand into his eye. That's—I
don't mean כנגד עינו, keneged eino, that's like directly hitting his eye,
you know? But רש״י Rashi seems to be that it was the
thing where you hit nearby and he got scared or something. Anyway,
alright. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. ואידך, ve'idach, so
פטור. patur. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר קרא ושיחתה amar kra veshichatah
עד שיתכוון. ad sheyitkaven. ואידך, ve'idach, משחת ושיחתה mishachat veshichatah נפקא. nafka.
No, it could have said ושחת, veshachat, why'd it say ושיחתה? veshichatah?
To tell you even a case of—even a case where you directly,
you know, tried to do
something—even the case where the person was already like born and alive
and you were trying to do something not on the eye, as
long as you weren't trying to hurt the eye, it's okay.
ואידך שחת ושיחתה לא דריש. ve'idach shachat veshichatah la darish. And the
other one says that he doesn't think that's a double language. Okay,
but that's interesting that the—particularly, I mean, I think רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל׳ס Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's position is a very logical one. It
has to be fundamentally a violent act. Whereas the רבנן Rabbanan say
it does not as long as you're trying to do something to
the eye or to the tooth. אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet:
הרי שהייתה עינו סמויה harei shehayeta eino smuya וחיטתה. vechitatah. Now let's
say that—was right, let's say he was already functionally blind because we've
been talking about making him blind, right? Making the tooth unusable. Let's
say he's already blind, but what you did was you—you gutted the
eye out. So you actually removed the eye from the socket, right?
So that's changing the body but not making it less functional.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says וחיטתה עבד יוצא בהן לחירות, vechitatah
eved yotzei bahen lecherut, he does go free. Okay. So מאי
טעמא?
mai ta'ama? מחוסר אבר הוא, mechusar eivar hu, because he's lacking a
limb and that's also considered to be a fundamental change of the
body even though it's not a functional difference.
כדברי בית שמאי. kedivrei Beit Shammai.
Right, well, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, but yes. Okay.
ותנא תונא, vetana tuna, we taught a—we
taught a ברייתא baraita
that supports this.
תמים וזכרות בבהמה ואין תמים וזכרות בעופות. tamim vezachrut bebehemah ve'ein tamim
vezachrut be'ofot.
It says, you know, by the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, it says
זכר תמים, zachar tamim, you know, it describes the animals that you
bring for sacrifices. So the requirement that it be male and that
it be unblemished is only by like sheep and goats and cows.
By bird sacrifices, it never says זכר תמים, zachar tamim, so it
can be female, it can be blemished, etc. I mean, there's some—there's
some larger animals that can also be female, but certainly there's no
requirement that it be unblemished. יכול יבשה גפה, yachol yavsha gapa, I
might think that if the wing has totally—I don't know, it's dried
up and withered, you know? נקטעה רגלה, nikte'a raglah, its leg is
cut off, נחטתה עינה, nechteta einah, its eye is—is gouged out, gorged
out, um, it would still be kosher because there's no הלכה halacha
about unblemished. תלמוד לומר מן העוף. talmud lomar min ha'of. It says
if you bring your sacrifice from the birds, ולא כל העוף, velo
kol ha'of, not all birds. Okay, so some birds are excluded. Which
birds are excluded? מחוסר אבר. mechusar eivar. Okay, so somehow we are
assuming that since there's an idea of מחוסר אבר mechusar eivar that
substantively... means that it's not just that it's imperfect, but it's seen
as something fundamentally a different type of a thing that would be
substantive enough that the slave would go free even if the eye
was already blind. Okay. So all right,
let's take a look.
And Rashi says, if you look at Rashi, Rashi assumes אלמא Alma
says Rashi אף על גב דסמיא מעיקרא af al gav de'sumya me'ikara
Rashi says the idea of blinding out the eye could be even
if the bird was already blind because it could be a bird
we said it could be blemished, so it could already be blind
and nevertheless somehow the final thing of gouging it out is considered
to be substantively different.
What is the limit though?
I know, I know, yeah, so that is a good point, but
again withered is not just not functional, that's somehow seen as already
you know like imagine that a person has like leprosy or gangrene
or whatever like in a limb is actually you know so that's
not just an issue of not functional.
אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi
amar Rav הייתה לו יתרת וחתכה. haitah lo yeteret ve'chatachah.
Let's say he had an extra finger and you cut off an
extra finger, עבד יוצא בה לחירות. eved yetzei bah le'cheirut. So you
still cut off a limb, okay, it doesn't matter that it was
an extra limb. אמר רב הונא והוא שנספרת על גב היד. Amar
Rav Huna vehu shenisperet al gav hayad. No, but that would only
be if like you would hold up the hand and you would
count it and you say one, two, three, four, five, six, you
know, it would be continuous with the other fingers, so then it's
considered part of your hand and it's considered this person has six
fingers and you cut off one of his fingers. But if it's
somehow sticking in a way that clearly it's not counted together with
the fingers of the hand, then that's considered I don't know some
hanging you know it's not considered a finger, okay, and we're going
to so it's only if you cut off as we'll see in
a minute what constitutes the limbs that actually you would go free.
Okay. סבי דנזוניא. Savei de'Nazunya. Now the elders of this place Nazunya
לא אתו לפירקיה דרב חסדא. lo atu le'pirkei de'Rav Chisda. They didn't
come to Rav Chisda's שיעור. shiur. אמר ליה לרב המנונא. Amar lei
le'Rav Hamnuna. So Rav Chisda says to Rav Hamnuna זיל צנעינהו. zil
tzne'inhu. Go put them in like put them in private which basically
is a nice way of saying like put them in חרם cherem
put them in נידוי niddui okay you know they should be put
into go sanction them in some way. That's what I could do
when my students don't come to my שיעור. shiur. Okay. אזל אמר
להו. Azal amar lehu.
So he went and he said to them. So you see Rabbi
Dovbo was here he'd appreciate this because rather than just you know
he wants to find out what's at the heart of it. So
he went and he said to them מאי טעמא לא אתו רבנן
לפירקא? Mai ta'ama lo atu rabbanan le'pirka? Why did the Rabbis not
come to the learning to the שיעור? shiur? So let's try and
understand you know what's motivating the students who are not showing up
to the שיעור. shiur. Okay. אמרו ליה amru lei they said to
him אמאי ניתו amai neitu why why should we come? דבעינא מיניה
מילתא ולא פשיט לן. de'ba'ina minei milta velo pashit lan. We asked
something from him and he didn't resolve it for us okay and
maybe they were saying that's an ongoing problem like he doesn't answer
our questions.
אמר להו מי בעיתו מינאי מידי ולא פשיטנא לכו? Amar lehu mi
ba'itu minai mi-dei velo pashitna lechu? Have you ever asked me something
I didn't answer for you? בעו מיניה. be'u minei. So meaning like
ask me your question, okay, which I'm not exactly is an answer
to why they should go to the שיעור shiur if the Rebbe
isn't answering the questions, but anyway ask me your question. So אמרו
ליה amru lei so they said at so I'm sorry so בעו
מיניה be'u minei they asked him עבד שסירסו רבו בביצים eved she'seiraso
rabo be'beitzim let's say a slave was made a
castrated by the testicles which is and they didn't cut off the
testicles but he crushed them or something of that nature okay מהו.
mahu. What's the story? כמום שבגלוי דמי. ke'mum sheba'galui dami. Is that
like a visible
blemish? Because we said on the one hand it's true we said
that it's enough to make something unfunctional, you don't have to cut
it away from the body like the eye. On the other hand
the Torah speaks about the eye and the tooth and we're going
to see in a minute that it refers that we're going to
include any type of a visible limb, a limb that is externally
visible, right? If he goes he sticks his hand inside of the
his throat and he you know I don't know whatever he does
you know let's say pulls out his tonsils or something like that
right does something internal injury you know it could be drastic but
he wouldn't go free right? Okay it has to be something that's
an external limb. So this the limb is external but the injury
is not really visible right because you know you don't see the
crushed testicle for example. Okay so I mean I wonder if I
wonder if always blinding an eye is visible to the other person
right? You know you can imagine hitting the eye and it and
it loses its sight and another person wouldn't be able to see
that.
It wouldn't necessarily mean when you're you know unclothed versus clothed.
Right, right
internal versus external. Right, that's the right thank you that's the better
way to say. Now the other thing could also be not just
that you can't see like that the testicle are crushed but you
can't see the testicles themselves that might also be related right? You
can sort of you can see their shape you can't actually see
them.
What about them now being unfunctional? The testicle?
Yes but it has to be you have to do that to
an to an external limb, to a limb that is visible. Okay
not to a limb that's not visible. So take a look at
Rashi כמום שבגלוי דמי. ke'mum sheba'galui dami. He actually says
last of the
lines from the top שהרי תלויים בכיס וניכרים מבחוץ או לאו הואיל
וטמונים תוך הכיס. she'harei tluyim be'kis ve'nikarim mi'bachutz o lav ho'il u'tmunim
toch ha'kis. So it seems like for Rashi right the person is
not
just is
internal. Right, how visible is that limb? And it has to be
only to an externally visible limb.
Okay, an injury like placing in the kidney.
Right, that would not go free. Exactly. But that's obvious because the
kidney is completely internal. It's not obvious with, you know, a priori,
but for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* once it assumes it has to
be an externally visible limb, but here the limb itself is only
like, you know, you sense its shape but you don't totally see
the limb. So is that considered to be visible or a visible
limb or not? Okay, עולא Ulla, *Ulla*. לא
הוה בידיה *lo hava biyadei*. So he didn't know the answer. So
you've got to love the irony. Did you ever ask me anything
I didn't answer? Oh wait, I don't know the answer to that
one. So לא הוה בידיה *lo hava biyadei*. אמרו לו *amru lo*,
מה שמך *ma shimcha*? They said to him, what's your name, buddy?
You were sent by רב Rav. הונא *Rav Huna*. אמר להו Amar
lehu, *amar lehu*, המנונא *Hamnuna*. My name is המנונא *Hamnuna*. אמרו ליה
*amru leih*, they said to him, לאו המנונא אלא קרנונא *lav Hamnuna
ela Karnuna*. Your name shouldn't be המנונא *Hamnuna* אלא קרנונא *ela Karnuna*.
So what does רש״י *Rashi* say? It means like a יושב קרנות
*yosheiv kranot* which means like, you know, you're a lazy bum. You
know, you don't even know the answer, you don't know the answer.
So they weren't very demanding, right? If the rabbi doesn't answer our
question, you don't know the answer, this and that. Anyway, תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* says that the word נונא *nuna* means a fish. So המנונא
*Hamnuna* sounds like חמנונא *Chamnuna* like a nice hot fish. And they
said you're not a hot fish, you're a cold fish. You're a
קרנונא *Karnuna*.
Okay,
exactly. Okay anyway, אתא לקמיה דרב חסדא *ata lekamei deRav Chisda*. So
he went to רב Rav חסדא *Rav Chisda* and he said, here's
why they said they weren't coming and anyway they asked me this
question and I didn't have the answer. אמר ליה *amar leih*, so
רב Rav חסדא *Rav Chisda* said, מתניתא בעו מינך *matnisa bo minach*.
What they asked you is effectively a משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. תנן *tnan*,
we taught in a משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. Now by the way you
have to point out, now we're going to forget about these guys
who didn't come to the שיעור *shiur*, but you have to point
out the irony that רב Rav, הונא *Rav Huna* did answer the
question but he answered it to המנונא *Hamnuna*. Presumably he wasn't, I
don't know, responding to them. They probably sounded like they were a
tough crowd. So maybe he didn't want to, okay, but anyway it's
quite fascinating the whole dynamic. Anyway, what's the answer to this? We
can get it from the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna*. תנן *tnan*, עשרים
וארבעה ראשי אברים שבאדם כולם אין מיטמאין משום מחיה *esrim ve'arba rashei
evarim she'ba'adam kulam ein metamin mishum michya*. Oh, it's very much connected
to this week's פרשה *parsha*, right. So the הלכה halacha, *halacha* is
that it says לכל מראה עיני הכהן *lechol marei einei hakohen*. So
the spot has to be visible to the eyesight of the כהן
kohen. *kohen*. So if it is on a sloped limb like on
a finger at the tip, the fingertip, and part of it goes
here and part of it goes here, you can't see all of
it together at the same time. I mean, you know, I guess
you know it would be impossible to see all of it in
one look. So that would not be a צרעת *tzara'at*. Okay? So
what we're going to deal now with is the limbs of the
body that are sloped. Not exactly the same as the עבד eved
*eved*. עבד eved *eved* you don't care about sloped or not, here
it's about whether it's visible, but we're going to be identifying the
sort of like limbs of the body. Okay, well that's also true.
עשרים וארבעה ראשי אברים שבאדם כולם אין מיטמאין משום מחיה *esrim ve'arba
rashei evarim she'ba'adam kulam ein metamin mishum michya*. Twenty-four of the heads
of the limbs, because of the sloping, sort of the slope on
both sides, אין מיטמאין משום מחיה *ein metamin mishum michya*. And it
has this sign of צרעת *tzara'at*, this מחיה *michya*, this healed space
spot, it's not a problem. ואלו הן *ve'eilu hen*. ראשי אצבעות ידים
ורגלים *rashei etzba'ot yadayim veraglayim*. So the ten toes and ten fingers,
that's twenty. וראשי אזנים *verashei oznayim*, the sort of edge of the
ear. If it went from one side of the ear, went over,
you know, the edge to the other side. Okay, that's twenty-two. וראש
החוטם *verosh hachotem*, the nose, which I don't really get because there's
something that is like this on the nose, you can sort of
see it, can't you? Maybe it means like maybe it's down here
and then going up here or something. Anyway, okay, so that's twenty-three.
וראש הגוייה *verosh hageviyah*,
the top of the penis. That's twenty-four. וראשי דדים שבאשה *verashei dadim
shebe'isha*, by a woman it would be the tops of the breasts.
רבי Rebbe, יהודה אומר omer *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, אף af שבאיש *af
shebe'ish*, even for a man
and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* feel that that's not sloped enough or
protruding enough to be that issue. Okay, what does that have to
do with us? ותני עלה *vetani ala*, ובכולם עבד יוצא בהן לחירות
*uvichulam eved yotzei bahen lacheirut*. Any of these a slave would go
free. These are all external limbs that could be cut, broken off,
okay, or broken at least. I mean, you know, the nose could
be broken and so on. So the slave would go free.
Okay, so that's twenty-six, these twenty-four plus the עין ושן *ayin vashen*.
Right. רבי Rebbe אומר *Rabbi omer*, אף הסירוס af ha-seerus, *af hasirus*.
Right. Now also plus if you cut off the whole leg, you
know, I don't know, that obviously would be something, cut off the
arm, right? And I mean what if say somebody already was had
an amputated foot, so you're not also cutting off the toes, and
then you cut off at the knee? Presumably that's also, right? רבי
Rebbe אומר *Rabbi omer*, אף הסירוס Af Hasirus *af hasirus*. Even and
presumably we're not going any we're going because we're not we're talking
about the injury here, so we're not talking about צרעת *tzara'at* anymore.
Now we're talking about a slave going free. Even somebody who castrated.
בן עזאי Ben Azai אומר *Ben Azzai omer*, אף הלשון af ha-lashon?
*af halashon*, cutting off the tongue. Ooh, that's interesting. אמר מר *amar
mar*. So now let's look at those two opinions, and clearly we're
talking at least with סירוס seerus. *sirus* we're talking about the slave.
רבי Rebbe אומר אף af הסירוס *Rabbi omer af hasirus*. סירוס seerus
דמאי *sirus demai*? What did you castrate? אילימא סירוס seerus דגיד *ilima
sirus degid*, היינו גוייה *hainu gviyah*. We already mentioned
that, right? That the penis was one of the ראשי אברים *rashei
evarim*. אלא לאו ella lav, סירוס sirus דביצים *ela lav sirus dbeitzim*?
It must be the testicles. So you see that that's considered to
be a that's your answer. That that makes a slave go free.
Now you could say what if you completely cut them away and
removed them? So again the question... So the question seems to be
not that the injury isn't visible, but that the limb itself was
not fully visible. So if you see that by castrating the testicles,
a slave would go free, it shows you that the testicles are
considered to be a visible limb. Okay, we'll get to the tongue.
Okay, so that's anyway that's the answer to our question, that they
are considered to be a visible limb, at least according to רבי,
Rebbe okay, but maybe בן עזאי Ben Azai. or the תנא קמא
Tana Kamma argues. רבי אומר אף סירוס. Rebbe omer af seerus.
So now we're going to continue now that we've answered our question,
but now we're going to keep on going. Even סירוס. For רבי,
Rebbe even the ones you added, but he didn't say the tongue,
that was בן עזאי. Ben Azai Would רבי Rebbe say that the
tongue is not considered, cutting the tongue he wouldn't go free? הא
ורמינהו, ha urminhu,
I'll ask you on this. הרי מי שהיה מזה, Harei mi shehaya
mazeh, there's another discussion about the tongue. Is the tongue considered an
externally visible part of the body or not? Okay. הרי מי שהיה
מזה, Harei mi shehaya mazeh, you were sprinkling the ashes of the
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Now the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, the ashes,
they don't have to cover your whole body. As long as one
little bit of the water with the ashes of the פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah touches some part of your body, you're טהור. tahor. But
it has to be an external part of your body. If you
opened your mouth and it went into your mouth, it wouldn't count.
But what if it goes on your tongue? Okay? Did it touch
an external part of your body or an internal part of your
body? You stuck out your tongue, bleh. Anyway, הרי שהיה מזה, harei
shehaya mazeh, you were sprinkling the water with the פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah ashes, ונזה הזה על פיו, v'nitza ha-hazeh al piv, and it
touched his mouth.
Now we're not yet at the tongue, but the mouth. We'll see
what that means in a minute. רבי אומר הזה, Rebbe omer hiza,
that counts. וחכמים אומרים לא הזה, Ve-chachamim omrim lo hiza, it does
not count. מאי לאו על
לשונו, Mai lav al leshono, presumably you mean the tongue, because if
it was just the lips, of course the lips are external. And
you see that for רבי Rebbe the tongue is considered an externally
visible part of the body. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא, על
שפתיו. lo, al sefatav. No, maybe we're talking about lips. The גמרא
Gemara says, על שפתיו, al sefatav, the lips? פשיטא, peshita, obviously that
would be external. And you could also ask why would the חכמים
Chachamim say it wouldn't count? No, מהו דתימא זימנא דחלים שפתיה, mahu
de-teima zimna de-chalim sefateih, sometimes you like, you know, purse your lips
together or smack them together, so you know, like this, so the
red of the lips isn't visible because you're like closing or squeezing
your mouth together. קא משמע לן Kama shema lan that no, since
most of the time they're visible, they're visible. It would make the
חכמים's chachamim position bizarre since sometimes you close your lips, it's not...
anyway, but the גמרא Gemara is going to move beyond that. ותניא
Ve-tanya no, you can't say that. We have a ברייתא Baraita that
says על לשונו al leshono explicitly that רבי Rebbe says that the
ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah on the tongue count as
on the external part of your body. ועוד תניא, Ve-od tanya, we
also taught a ברייתא, Baraita, ושניטל רוב הלשון, ve-sh'nital rov ha-lashon, and
if the majority of the tongue is removed, then that's considered to
be a מום. mum. Okay, a מום mum also by an animal
is only if it's a blemish, an external blemish. Okay, if an
animal has some internal thing and it's not a טריפה, tereifah, it's
not a מום. mum. So רבי Rebbe says if the majority of
the tongue of an animal is removed, it's a blemish. So again
you see that's considered external.
רוב הלשון, rov ha-lashon, the תנא קמא Tana Kamma says the majority.
רבי אומר רוב המדבר שבלשון, Rebbe omer rov ha-medaber she-ba-lashon,
it's the talking part of the tongue, which means the part from...
no, from what's that thing called at the keep of the tongue,
what? I'm sorry? Uvula?
Yeah, the uvula. You know when...
so
anyway, from the part from where the uvula towards the front, that's
considered המדבר. ha-medaber. Okay, so I guess it's, I'm guessing that's the
one that's right. So anyway, so anyway, רבי Rebbe says that's the
part that's defined as the tongue or that's defined as external. So
anyway you see for רבי Rebbe a tongue is external. So if
a tongue is external for רבי Rebbe, and both for the ashes
of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and for a מום, mum, why
would he say that an עבד does not go free, assuming that
they all have the same
definition? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לאו, fine. רבי אומר סירוס
ולא מיבעיא לשון. Rebbe omer seerus ve-lo mibaya lashon. Fine, when רבי
Rebbe says castrating with testicles, it would, and certainly the tongue. You
know, the tongue at least you see the tongue, you never actually
see the testicles. So רבי Rebbe says when he says castrated, he
means and you know it goes without saying that the tongue would,
the עבד would go free. בן עזאי אומר לשון. Ben Azai omer
lashon. And בן עזאי Ben Azai. says no, only the tongue, not
the testicles. So the issue of the testicles is a debate of
רבי Rebbe and בן עזאי. Ben Azai So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אבל לשון לא? aval lashon lo? So בן עזאי Ben
Azai would reject the tongue idea? ומאי אף? U-mai af? So why
does בן עזאי Ben Azai say אף הלשון? af ha-lashon, He just
said it was only הלשון. ha-lashon. So אקמייתא, a-kamaisa, no, אף is
adding to the תנא קמא's Tana Kamma list. The תנא קמא Tana
Kamma only had twenty-four, רבי Rebbe added סירוס which means סירוס plus
לשון, lashon, and בן עזאי Ben Azai said אף לשון, af lashon,
he's not adding to רבי, Rebbe, he's going back to the תנא
קמא. Tana Kamma. I'm going to add לשון lashon to the תנא
קמא's Tana Kamma list. With רבי Rebbe, that goes without saying, but
that's what he's doing.
רבי Rebbe, also considered it part of the גלוי.
galui. Right. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says that this is
a very confusing way of writing the ברייתא. Baraita. אי הכי נתני
בן עזאי ברישא. Ee hachi nasnei Ben Azai bereisha. If so, let
בן עזאי Ben Azai be taught first. It should have said the
תנא קמא Tana Kamma should have said twenty-four, בן עזאי Ben Azai.
should have said אף הלשון, and then רבי Rebbe. should have said
אף הסירוס, right? Because then
רבי Rabbi, is
including even more than בן עזאי. Ben Azai So the גמרא Gemara
says no, תנא סמך לדרבי וקבעה. tana samakh l'de-Rebbe ve-kav'ah. Originally we
didn't know about בן עזאי's Ben Azzai position. It's so funny, who's
the תנא, tana, it's not רבי, Rabbi, רבי, Rabbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא
Rebbe Yehuda Ha-Nasi is the one who's writing the, anyway, maybe it's
רבי, Rabbi. maybe it acknowledges that there could be a later author,
you know, who you know, of the משנה Mishnah, that whatever, you
know, later than רבי. Rabbi Because there are משניות Mishnayot that were
added. And then it heard that
בן עזאי Ben Azzai had said אף הסירוס going on the תנא
קמא, Tanna Kamma, not going on רבי, Rebbe
but you already had
the משנה mishnah with רבי, Rebbe, so you weren't going to insert
בן עזאי Ben Azzai in the middle of the משנה, mishnah? you
tagged him onto the end. Okay, so
ותני משנה לא זז ממקומו, v'tani mishna lo zaz m'komo, you didn't
change the original form of the משנה, mishnah. just because once you
learn a text in one way, it's hard to unlearn it in
another way. So בן עזאי Ben Azzai. got tagged onto the end
even though the אף is a little confusing because according to the
way the גמרא Gemara is reading it, he's more limiting than רבי,
Rebbe not more than רבי. Rebbe Anyway, what we said
is שריטה, s'rata, that's a separate question.
Right, שריטה s'rata is a separate question. Right,
especially if it was an orally memorized text, absolutely,
absolutely. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has said that סירוס effectively
is a debate of רבי and בן עזאי. Okay, but now we're
going to actually discuss a little bit more about this issue of
the tongue, which is interesting. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, said עולא, הכל מודים בלשון לענין
טומאה דגלוי הוא אצל שרץ. hakol modim bilashon l'inyan tumah d'galuye hu
etzel sheretz. Everybody agrees for the tongue if it comes to, there's
another הלכה, halacha if you touch a טמא tamei object with an
inside of your body and not the outside of your body, you're
not טמא. tamei. So if somebody basically, if you were, you know,
took a piece of נבילה neveilah and stuck it into the inside
of your teeth, right, and no part of your external part of
your body touched it, you would not be טמא, tamei, okay, because
it says, it's learned from a פסוק pasuk that says ידיו לא
שטף במים, yadav lo shutaf bamayim, that what that means is that
it has to be like touching with the hands, with an external
part of your body.
נבלת העוף. Nivlas ha-of.
Right, נבלת העוף nivlas ha-of is a special הלכה halacha of נבלת
העוף.
nivlas ha-of. It's referred to as a כלי kli where the inside
and the outside...
oh right, a כלי kli is only טמא tamei on the inside.
That's a good point. Okay, okay. By the way, it's also true
in the reverse, if there's something טמא tamei inside of your body,
the גמרא Gemara discusses what if you have a ring that touched
a dead body or something and somebody swallowed it, okay, it would
not cause טומאה tum'ah even under an אהל ohel or whatever. Okay,
but anyway, but here we're talking about touching the טמא tamei thing.
So if your tongue touches a טמא tamei thing, everybody considers that
it's considered like you touched it,
אשר יגע בו אמר רחמנא, asher yiga bo amra rachmana, because when
it talks about touching a טמא tamei object, it says touching it,
והיינו מבר נגיעה הוא, v'hainu mibar n'giah hu, so it's like, you
know, you use your tongue to touch things, you can touch things
with your tongue, okay, so it's a natural way of, you know,
you can do it. So therefore, even though you could say the
object of the tongue might be somewhat of an internal object because
it's kept in your mouth most of the time and it's not
seen externally, nevertheless here the emphasis is on an act of touching.
So when it comes to an act of touching, we say normally
an act of touching requires touching with an external part of your
body, not an internal, but seen through the lens of an act
of touching, a tongue is definitely a way to touch. And therefore,
from that lens, it's considered an external part of your body because
look, a tongue sometimes is visible. Okay, לענין טבילה, l'inyan tvilah,
and everybody would agree when it would come to going into the
מקוה mikvah where the water has to touch the, you know, external
surface of your body, you don't have to open up your mouth
and have it touch your tongue, so everybody says no, כטמון דמי,
k'tamun dami, that's considered something buried in your body and not external
and does not have to come in contact with water. מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? ורחץ בשרו במים אמר רחמנא. V'rachatz besaro
bamayim amra rachmana. It says you should wash your flesh with water.
מה בשרו מבר, Mah besaro mibar, the same way your flesh is
external, אף כל מבר, af kol mibar, everything is external. Now, okay,
but again, but the tongue is, so a tongue isn't external. But
again, but you said it was external when it came to touching.
So the bigger difference is that fundamentally we start with, it's not
as external as your skin, right, your skin is obviously there, but
also, I think as I said before or as the גמרא Gemara
said, you know, the emphasis of touching is an act of touching,
there clearly a tongue is in that category. But when it's a
question about similar to your skin, you know, that type of surface
area and external surface, not.
So why are you told to brush your teeth before going to
the מקוה? mikvah?
Well, we're going to get to that actually. Okay, so now
רש"י Rashi has another reason because רש"י Rashi is still bothered why
do we assume that this is telling you a different definition. So
in addition to the emphasis on the act of touching, רש"י Rashi
says if you look at רש"י Rashi about six lines from the
bottom, רש"י Rashi says, ולאו מבר ולא שיכנס מים לתוך הפה ואף
להוציא כל הלשון אינו יכול. v'lav mibar v'lo sheikanes mayim l'toch hapah
v'af l'hotzi kol halashon eino yachol. You can't get your whole tongue
out, okay, or covered it ובטבילה למקוה לא אשכחן אבל נגיעה בכל
שהוא הוי נגיעה. u'btvila l'mikvah lo ashkechan aval n'giah b'kol shehu avei
n'giah. So רש"י Rashi says like another logic, if we were to
say the tongue was external, it would have to touch all of
the surface of your tongue which isn't feasible,
but to
do an act of touching you can touch with part of your
tongue. Okay, so anyway, so for touching טומאה tum'ah your tongue is
external and for טבילה tvilah it's internal. Okay, now, לא נחלקו, lo
nechlaku, this is such a nice way of framing the debate, אלא
לענין הזאה ela l'inyan haza'ah when it comes to this issue about
the sprinkling of the water with the ashes of the פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah.
רבי מדמי ליה לטומאה, Rebbe medame lei letumah, רבי says it's like
טומאה tumah because you're coming to be מטהר metaher something from being
טמא, tamei, so therefore the tongue is included and any if it
touches the tongue it's okay because the tongue is an external object
for purposes of becoming טמא. tamei. ורבנן מדמו ליה לטבילה, V'rabanan medamu
lei letvila, no, you're becoming טהור tahor here, not טמא, tamei, and
therefore the tongue is not considered an external so the water touching
the tongue doesn't work. ותרוייהו בהאי קרא קמיפלגי, V'tarvayhu bihai k'ra k'miflagi,
they debate the following פסוק. posuk. והזה הטהור על הטמא, V'hizah hatahor
al hatame, the pure person shall sprinkle on the טמא. tamei. רבי
סבר והזה הטהור על הטמא ביום השלישי וביום השביעי וחטאו, Rebbe savar
v'hizah hatahor al hatame biyom hashlishi uvyom hashvii v'chito, and then there's
another word, sprinkle and he purifies him. So you see it emphasizes
there's no connection yet to an act of טבילה, tevilah, but it
emphasizes the word טמא, tamei, so it's like you become טמא, tamei,
it's your tongue is the object of becoming טמא, tamei, so the
הזאה hazah works on the tongue. ורבנן סברי V'rabanan savri no, וחטאו
ביום השביעי וכבס בגדיו ורחץ במים v'chito biyom hashvii v'kibes begadav v'rachatz
bamayim is the פסוק posuk ends with going to the מקוה. mikvah.
So therefore it's like going to the מקוה mikvah and the tongue
is internal for those purposes. Okay, so it doesn't count when it
goes on the tongue. ורבנן נמי נדמיו לטומאה, V'rabanan nami nidmeyu letumah,
why don't they compare it to טומאה? tumah? The beginning of the
פסוק posuk is right, והזה הטהור על הטמא? v'hizah hatahor al hatame?
No, טהרה מטהרה הוי ליה למילף, tahara mitahara havei leh lemelaf, they'd
rather learn a process of purifying. טהרה tahara from טהרה, tahara, going
to the מקוה mikvah purifies, the water with the פרה אדומה parah
adumah ashes purifies, so we'll say if the tongue is considered internal
for one, it's internal for both.
ורבי נדמיו לטבילה, V'Rebbe nidmeyu letvila, how about רבי, why doesn't he
make that comparison? וכבס בגדיו הפסיק הענין, v'khibes begadav hifsik hainyan, no,
because there's another verb before it gets to going to the טבילה,
tevilah, it says וכבס בגדיו ורחץ בשרו במים. v'khibes begadav v'rachatz besaro
bamayim. So clearly we're onto a different topic in the פסוק posuk
when we talk about טבילה, tevilah, so we're not going to compare
it to טבילה, tevilah, we're going to compare it to טומאה tumah
and say the tongue is considered external. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, וסבר רבי לענין טבילה כטמון דמי, v'savar Rebbe le'inyan
tevilah ketamun dami, here's Michael's question, can you really say that the
tongue is considered to be like you know buried or whatever not
external and doesn't have to get the מקוה mikvah water? ואמר רבין
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה אמר רב יצחק, v'amar Ravin amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava amar Rav Yitzchak, מעשה בשפחתו של בית רבי, maase
beshifchato shel beis Rebbe, there was a story with a maidservant in
רבי's household. שטבלה ועלתה ונמצא עצם בין שניה, shetevela v'alta v'nimtza etzem
bein shineha,
she went to the מקוה mikvah presumably in order so that she
went she handled the food she would not make it טמא, tamei,
and when she came out there was a little bone, purifies it
right? Yeah, there was a bone, that's true guys he wasn't a
כהן. There was a little bone that was between her teeth, okay,
והצריכה רבי טבילה אחרת, v'hitrichah Rebbe tevilah acheres, and רבי said go
back to the מקוה. mikvah. So you see the מקוה mikvah water
presumably has to cover the inside surfaces of the mouth. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, נהי דביאת מים לא בעינן מקום הראוי לבוא
בו מים בעינן. n'hi debiyas mayim lo be'inan makom harauy lavo bo
mayim be'inan. We don't need מקוה mikvah water to actually come in
contact with the inside of the mouth, but this is called בית
הסתרים beis hastarim by the way. בית הסתרים beis hastarim is the
places which are like orifices, you know that water something could come
into but they're not surface areas. Also included
would be let's say I guess the opening of the anus, the
opening of the vagina, the eye, I mean underneath the eyelid or
something like this, what's in your yeah right inside of your ear,
ear would be a better example, right. So those are considered to
be what yeah you don't have to keep your eyes open when
you go underwater right which is actually interesting because you can actually
see the eye, right, but it's considered still בית הסתרים beis hastarim
because I because the eyelid tends to cover, okay. Actually not only
that, it's very interesting, there's even something of בית הקמטים beis hakamatin
which is the natural folds of your body that if right that
if something is actually water doesn't even have to get into a
surface that's naturally just not you know that's naturally not visible because
of a natural like bodily fold,
right. Exactly, exactly. So anyway, but even though the water doesn't have
to come into contact with it, it needs to be free of
חציצה, chatzitzah, it needs to be able to have water come in
contact with it, okay. כרבי זירא, K'Rebbe Zeira, like
רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira, אמר רבי זירא כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה
מעכבת בו ושאינו ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. amar Rebbe Zeira kol
harauy lebila ein bila me'akeves bo, v'she'eino rauy lebila bila me'akeves bo.
So this is the famous saying, the הלכה halacha is that if
you say a min- if you're going to bring a מנחה mincha
of sixty עשרון, isaron, so then you then that's fine even if
you don't mix it with the oil because we say that that's
at least theoretically mixable with the oil. But if you say you're
going to bring one of sixty-one עשרון isaron then you have to
divide it into สอง מנחות minchos because that's not even theoretically mixable.
Okay, so it has to be fit to be mixed with the
oil, doesn't have to get, here too it has to be fit
for the water to come in contact but doesn't have to actually.
Now תוספות Tosafos asks the obvious question which is how do you
know when the תורה Torah actually demands that it be that something
be done and how do you know when it's enough that it's
just fit for it to be done? Like why don't we say,
well, I don't have to actually pick up my לולב, lulav, it
just has to be fit for being picked up, right? How do
you decide when it needs to be really done? So תוספות Tosfos
says well partly it has to do with the question about the
תורה's Torah actually telling you to do an act like take your
לולב, lulav, you've got to do the act. But if the תורה
Torah is telling you about like the מנחה's mincha a good example
because the מנחה mincha says בלול בשמן, balul bashamen, it's describing the
object of the מנחה, mincha, it's something mixed with oil. It doesn't
tell you you must mix. So mixed could mean that describes the
nature of the object, so if it has that potential. So that's
enough to satisfy the nature of the object. Okay, now how about
the בית הסתרים? Beis Hastarim? That's like less clear, but so תוספות
Tosfos says if you look at the י"ח עמוד ב', yud chet
amud beis, תוספות Tosfos. says like this,
ויש לומר, v'yeish lomar, it's about eight lines before the word בהמה
behema before the next תוספות. Tosfos Okay, it says לאו לבעי, lav
livai, it says... the גמרא Gemara says ויש לומר, v'yeish lomar, דודאי
שינה הכתוב בלול כמה פעמים. d'vadai shina hakatuv balul kama pe'amim. It
says the word "mixed" many times, lines תוספות Tosafot in בלול balul
here. אבל לא כתב בלשון ציווי. Aval lo kasav bilshon tzivui. Okay?
ובלילה מצוה בלאו למימנא אלא ראוי. U'blila mitzva b'lav l'meimna ela ra'ui.
So it means it doesn't say you must, it's just describing it.
ואם תאמר בטבילה מנא לן דבעינן ראוי. V'im tomar b'tvila mena lan
d'beinan ra'ui. Okay, how do you know that this middle stage, fit
but it doesn't have to happen? ויש לומר משום דכתיב רחץ את
כל בשרו. v'yeish lomar mishum d'ksiv rachatz es kol besaro. דמשמע אפילו
בית הסתרים. D'mashma afilu beis hastarim. The כל בשרו kol besaro is
coming to include even the בית הסתרים. beis hastarim. So that tells
you that's on the one
hand. But then דכתיב וידיו, d'ksiv v'yadav, but there's another פסוק pasuk
that speaks about the hand, מה ידיו מבוראי אף כל מבוראי, ma
yadav mibora'ei af kol mibora'ei, וממעטים בית הסתרים. u'mema'atim beis hastarim. So
we have like a contradiction: one emphasizes external, the כל kol is
saying internal. So the way we resolve those different things is we
say, well, it means it doesn't have to actually come in contact,
but it has to be fit for coming into contact. Okay, so
that's a fascinating question about when do you say something is in
this middle step, that doesn't have to happen but has to be
fit for happening. Some ראשונים rishonim say that because they can't explain
like they don't buy תוספות'ס Tosfos's answer and they can't explain why
by טבילה tvila because טבילה tvila says you are טובל, tovel, it
speaks about an act of טבילה. tvila. It's not like the מנחה
mincha where it describes the nature of the מנחה, mincha, בלול. balul.
It says you are טובל, tovel, so a number of ראשונים rishonim
say that the only way to explain בית הסתרים beis hastarim is
to say that it's only דרבנן. derabbanan. That if it were a
דאורייתא deoraisa need for בית הסתרים, beis hastarim, then it wouldn't, then
you would really need it to come in contact with water. Okay,
but so according to a number of ראשונים, rishonim, בית הסתרים beis
hastarim is only דרבנן. derabbanan. That's as I said, that's in general
an interesting question about when do we say partial is enough, when
do we say potential is enough, and when do we say that
you really need it to take place.
Does it make a difference according to this? Meaning if it's only
דרבנן, derabbanan, she really was יוצאת. yotzes.
Right. Yeah, I mean, no, it's דרבנן, derabbanan, but the דרבנן derabbanan
said that it's פסול pasul even בדיעבד. b'di'eved. But there are cases
where an issue like this does come up that's very relevant for
פוסקים poskim dealing with שאלות, sheilos, like somebody who has an ear
infection and needs to have something in their ear or whatever other
types of things. So Rav Ovadia Yosef mostly
follows the approach that בית הסתרים beis hastarim is דרבנן, derabbanan, which
gives him like more latitude. Which isn't to say that immediately בדיעבד
b'di'eved you could say okay, because the general הלכה is בדיעבד b'di'eved
is not good. But it means that then you could rely on
certain שיטות, shitos, you know, to say it's okay. All right, brace...
brace yourselves, everyone. Okay, now כתנאי. kesannai. This issue, back to whether
a crushed testicles is considered a visible מום mum or מום mum
on a visible limb, the גמרא Gemara says it's a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. ומה הוא? U'ma hu? And this is the פסוק pasuk
by
a... by a blemish: מעוך וכתות ונתוק וכרות.
Ma'uach v'kasus
v'nasuk v'karus. כולם בביצים, Kulam b'veitzim, all of this refers to the
testicles, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. The גמרא Gemara asks בביצים
ולא בגיד? B'veitzim v'lo b'gid? Only the testicles and, you know, not
in the actual penis itself? אלא כולם אף בביצים, Ela kulam af
b'veitzim, even the testicles, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov אומר כולם בגיד, Kulam b'gid, only
on the penis; on the testicles, that would not be considered visible.
Again, it's not like, you know, you couldn't say that you see
that something happened to the testicles, but presumably the limb isn't visible.
Okay, so since for... I mean, I guess if the scrotum was
detached, that would be a different story, that's visible. But if something
happens to the testicles without it happening to the scrotum, and therefore
he would say that that's not considered a visible limb. Okay, and
therefore it's not a מום. mum. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר אף
בכולם בביצים. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer af b'kulam b'veitzim. רבי יוסי
אומר מעוך וכתות אף בביצים, נתוק וכרות בגיד אין בביצים לא. Rabbi
Yossi omer ma'uach v'kasus af b'veitzim, nasuk v'karus b'gid in b'veitzim lo.
So the מעוך וכתות, ma'uach v'kasus, the crushed, that applies even to
the... to the testicles, because somehow that is somehow visible, whereas the
נתוק וכרות, nasuk v'karus, the detached, not. Now, that sounds funny. Detached
seems like the most visible. But that's if you think about the
scrotum being detached. If you think about the testicles being detached inside
of the scrotum, so you're saying well, that's not so visible to
the external eye. But if you think about them somehow being crushed,
maybe, again, I'm not exactly clear. If you look at רש"י... Rashi...
רש"י Rashi says מעוך וכתות אף בביצים דמינכר טפי. ma'uach v'kasus af
b'veitzim de'minkar tefei. Maybe because again, the shape changes, so you can
see a difference in the nature of the shape if they've been
crushed as opposed to detached. But it does raise the interesting question:
are we talking about the limb being visible? Then you can't distinguish
between what injury occurred to it. If the limb as... wasn't visible,
then it's never visible. He seems to be questioning whether the injury
is visible, okay, at least for the issue about the מום, mum,
right? What makes an animal a מום mum could be, is the
injury visible? Whereas what makes an animal... what makes a slave go
free, that might have to do with what type of limb we're
talking about. So not exactly clear you can equate the two. Okay,
moving on. Now,
we're done with... well, that was a very uneasy סוגיא sugya to
end with, but whatever. Anyway, we're done with human beings as objects
of קניינים, kinyanim, whether they're considered like אישות ishus which is something
that may
be... עבד כנעני Eved Canaani which is totally like property, on the
other hand, he doesn't lose his human status but there is a
full property identity to him. And now we move away from human
beings to animals, okay? So livestock, there's life, not inanimate, okay? But
now that's the next stage.
Let's take a look.
בהמה גסה נקנית במסירה, Behema Gasa nikneit bimesira, a large animal, like
a cow or a horse as opposed to a sheep or goat,
you are קונה koneh by מסירה mesira which is handing over the
reins, or handing over the, picking hold of the saddle, or something
of that nature. והדקה בהגבהה, Vehadaka behagbaha, and the small animals like
the grazing, the sheep and the goats, that's by lifting it up,
because they can be lifted up. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir,
that's what Rabbi Meir says. Let me read it. Let me talk
about it then it's much better. רבי אליעזר וחכמים אומרים בהמה דקה
נקנית במשיכה. Rabbi Eliezer vechachamim omrim behema daka nikneit bimshicha. No, a
small animal is משיכה mshicha not בהגבהה. behagbaha. Now, there's a lot
of interesting questions here, okay? One,
let's start with the following, which is, I'll just do a brief
one, I'll sort of summarize these big תוספותס. Tosafots. The brief one
about מסירה mesira is a question about that
can you just, is just grabbing hold, is that מסירה? mesira? מסירה
mesira suggests handing over, okay? And there's a גמרא Gemara, that actually
says that you can't be קונה koneh a lost object with מסירה.
mesira. This indicates that you actually need to be handed over by
the owner, which makes sense if you're not moving it, and you're,
you know, so the meaningful act of handing the reins over, okay,
but תוספות Tosafot discusses there are other גמרות Gemarot that make it
sound that you don't need to physically hand over the reins. So
תוספות Tosafot actually says that when the owner says לך חזק וקני,
lech chazak uknei, okay, that counts as, that verbal instruction to tell
you to do it counts as an act of handing over. So
if I say to Michael, Michael says will you sell me your
cow, I say sure, how much, a hundred dollars, great, deal, okay,
and then Michael goes and grabs it, so even though it's clear
I've agreed to sell it to him, that's not מסירה. mesira. But
if I say go take hold of the reins, and he takes
hold of the reins, I don't have to physically hand it over.
Okay, so that's at least what תוספות Tosafot says, that's at least
that's defining the act of מסירה. mesira. Now, let's talk about the
difference about הגבהה hagbaha versus משיכה mshicha and so on. הגבהה Hagbaha
is considered to be the best קנין, kinyan, like you lift it
up, you show total mastery, you're totally controlling it, and so on.
משיכה Mshicha less so. Now, there's a general presumption here, okay, that
is, that we could decide that, in many cases, we sort of
do decide
that you must do a better קנין kinyan if it's possible, and
not a weaker one, okay? So if I'm going to say that
הגבהה hagbaha is a reasonable thing to request, you know, from a
בהמה דקה, behema daka, I might actually say like only הגבהה, hagbaha,
not משיכה. mshicha. הגבהה, Hagbaha, right? And now on the other hand,
I might say no, no, הגבהה hagbaha is like, I'm not saying
you can't, you lift up a sheep, of course you would be
קונה, koneh, but like fundamentally I'm going to say that that's not
really a normal type of a קנין, kinyan, like that's not the
most viable, and I'm going to emphasize משיכה. mshicha. So for example,
look at רש"י, Rashi, okay, take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says בהגבהה, behagbaha, רש"י Rashi says ולא במשיכה. velo bimshicha. Okay,
so there's a presumption that you, what we have to do is
we have to identify a hierarchy of קניינים, kinyanim, okay, which is
the stronger one, which one demonstrates more ownership? And the importance of
demonstrating a hierarchy is that if I say, if I'm going to
be a, come along and say it's קונה בהגבהה, koneh behagbaha, what
I'm going to mean is only הגבהה, hagbaha, it's also a way
of like parsing my words, I'm going to mean only הגבהה hagbaha
and not things that are lower on the list, okay, because there's
a presumption that there's a hierarchy. If I say משיכה, mshicha, I
mean even משיכה, mshicha, okay? So the debate of משיכה mshicha versus
הגבהה hagbaha is, of course הגבהה hagbaha would demonstrate, okay, but the
question is, since הגבהה hagbaha is possible, is משיכה mshicha enough to
demonstrate? Or are we always going to demand הגבהה? hagbaha? So it's
always going to be a question to identify what's the hierarchy. So
when the חכמים chachamim say, when it says דקה בהגבהה, daka behagbaha,
it means not משיכה, mshicha, and the חכמים say משיכה, mshicha, it
means even משיכה, mshicha, okay? So that's one issue. So the question
within this, the big part of the big next question in תוספות
Tosafot is where does מסירה mesira fit on this list, okay? Presumably
הגבהה hagbaha is always the biggest, best. So if I can manage
to lift up a cow, okay, and we'll discuss that in a
minute, everybody would say it's okay. But nobody says you need, or
nobody that we've seen, we'll see in a minute in the גמרא,
Gemara. says you need הגבהה hagbaha by בהמה גסה. behema gasa. But
what it does say is that you need מסירה mesira by בהמה
גסה. behema gasa. Can I do משיכה? mshicha? Which is higher on
the list? When I say מסירה, mesira, do I mean even משיכה
mshicha or only מסירה? mesira? Is it clear the question here? Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara דרש רבא
בקימחוניה, Darash Rava bikimchunya, Rava... gave a דרשה drashah in this place,
קימכוניא. Kimchunia. בהמה גסה נקנית במשיכה. Behemah Gassah niknas b'meshichah. You do
it with משיכה. meshichah. Okay now, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says, I'm sorry, let's see another line. So אשכחו שמואל
לתלמידי דרב. Ashkechu Shmuel l'talmidei deRav. שמואל Shmuel found the students of
רב. Rav אמר להו, he said to them, מי אמר רב בהמה
גסה נקנית במשיכה? Mi amar Rav Behemah Gassah niknas b'meshichah? Did רב
Rav really say משיכה? meshichah? והאנן במסירה תנן. Ve'hanan b'mesirah tnan. Our
משנה mishnah. says מסירה. mesirah. ורב נמי אמסירה אמר. V'Rav nami a'mesirah
amar. And רב Rav also was known to say מסירה. mesirah. So
what's he doing saying משיכה? meshichah? So the גמרא Gemara. says, הדר
ביה מההיא. Hadar beih mehahi. You know what? He retracted his position.
He stopped saying מסירה, mesirah, he started saying משיכה. meshichah. Now, I
just need to pause for a moment and say, which one includes
the other? Right? Which is higher on the list? So if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, I'm sorry, where am I?
I'm sorry, no, not רש"י Rashi yet, not the רש"י. Rashi. I'm
sorry, let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara I'm sorry, and I
misread that last line. So the גמרא Gemara says, הדר ביה מההיא?
Hadar beih mehahi? So did רב, so this is שמואל Shmuel talking,
did רב retract his position and stop saying that a בהמה גסה
Behemah Gassah is מסירה? mesirah? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הוא
דאמר כי האי תנא. Hu d'amar ki hai tanna. He says like
the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita,
וחכמים אומרים... v'Chachamim omrim... like
רב
said משיכה.
meshichah. What about our משנה? mishnah. So רב said like the following
תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, וחכמים אומרים
זו וזו נקנית במשיכה. v'Chachamim omrim zo v'zo niknas b'meshichah. Both גסה
gassah and דקה dakka are with משיכה. meshichah. רבי שמעון אומר זו
וזו בהגבהה. Rabbi Shimon omer zo v'zo b'hagbah. Both are with הגבהה.
hagbah. Now we're going to get to a minute about how do
you do
הגבהה hagbah by a cow? Okay, but again, בהגבהה b'hagbah clearly means
only הגבהה hagbah because הגבהה hagbah is the top of the hierarchy.
What still isn't clear though is this debate of בהמה גסה, Behemah
Gassah, מסירה mesirah or משיכה, meshichah, which one includes the other? Okay,
so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, where is the
רש"י? Rashi?
Oh, it's the רש"י Rashi on the משנה. I'm sorry, it's the
רש"י Rashi on the משנה. נקנית במסירה. Niknas b'mesirah. Look at רש"י
Rashi on the
משנה. והלה מוסרה לו לקונה באפסר או בשער כדתניא לעיל היכי דמי
מסירה. V'haleh mosrah lo lakoneh b'afsar o b'sa'ar k'detanya l'eil heichi dami
mesirah. אבל משיכה לא מקניא דאין דרכה בכך לילך לפניו. Aval meshichah
lo maknya d'ein darchah b'chach lilech lefanav. So רש"י Rashi says מסירה
mesirah is higher on the hierarchy. If you say מסירה, mesirah, you
mean not משיכה. meshichah. Now why is משיכה meshichah not as good
says רש"י? Rashi? Very interesting. Because you don't make the animals walk
in front of you. Think about it, that you lead a cow
and you lead a
horse, but with goats and sheep, you're walking behind and you're pushing
them in front. Now if you ask me, I find this רש"י
Rashi fascinating. I always thought משיכה meshichah meant I'm drawing them to
me, that I'm leading. So רש"י Rashi says, no, you know why
משיכה meshichah doesn't work? Because fundamentally משיכה meshichah is that you're behind
them and making them move forward, which is so not how I
normally think about משיכה. meshichah. Anyway, what's important though is רש"י Rashi
says that when it says מסירה, mesirah, it means מסירה mesirah not
משיכה. meshichah. Okay, so the debate is whether a בהמה גסה Behemah
Gassah is מסירה, mesirah, do we mean מסירה mesirah and not משיכה?
meshichah? תוספות Tosafot says different. תוספות Tosafot says משיכה meshichah is much
better, right? If you think about it, תוספות Tosafot makes sense. מסירה
mesirah you're just holding
onto something. משיכה meshichah you do more, you move the animal. So
everybody agrees משיכה meshichah works. The question is do we allow מסירה
mesirah to work by a בהמה גסה? Behemah Gassah? Since it's such
a big animal, they are more stationary, you know, sheep you move
much more quickly or whatever. You know, so the question is do
we allow מסירה mesirah to work by a big animal? So that's
one, right, that's one debate. In all these times when somebody says
X, does X mean even X, or does X mean X and
not Y? Okay, which is considered to be the more obvious one?
All right. Now in theory sometimes I should say it's not necessarily
a hierarchy. Like somebody could be of the position that by a
בהמה דקה Behemah Dakka only משיכה meshichah not מסירה, mesirah, and by
a בהמה גסה Behemah Gassah only מסירה mesirah and not משיכה, meshichah,
right? And that somehow it's like because it's not meaningful. You don't
hand over reins of a sheep. So it's not because one is
better or worse, it's that it's not meaningful. Some things are more
meaningful for one and more meaningful for the others, so things could
be mutually exclusive. משיכה meshichah could be not מסירה mesirah and מסירה
mesirah not משיכה. meshichah. But anyway, in general we assume a hierarchy.
And there's the debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot is, when
we're debating מסירה mesirah by בהמה גסה, Behemah Gassah, according to רש"י
Rashi it means מסירה mesirah and משיכה meshichah won't work, and for
תוספות Tosafot it means even מסירה mesirah will work by a בהמה
גסה, Behemah Gassah, by a large animal. Okay, so that's another debate.
Now the final thing is a position that even a בהמה גסה
Behemah Gassah requires הגבהה. hagbah. Clearly הגבהה hagbah is at the top
of the hierarchy. So the one who says הגבהה, hagbah, who said
הגבהה? hagbah? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can only do הגבהה.
hagbah. So how are you going to do הגבהה hagbah by a
cow or by a horse? And the גמרא Gemara has an even
better question and we'll end with this and now we'll have caught
up and this will be fun. מתקיף לה רב יוסף, Matkif lah
Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked him this, אלא מעתה פיל
לרבי שמעון במה יקנה? Ela me'ata pil l'Rabbi Shimon b'meh yikneh? How
would you be קונה koneh an elephant?
So אמר ליה
אביי,
Amar
leih
Abaye, all right, that you wouldn't do הגבהה. hagbah. בחליפין, B'chalifin, you
do that with a קנין סודר. kinyan sudar. אי נמי בשכירות מקומו,
I nami b'schirut mekomo, or you'd rent the
space. like things like on a circus and you have it step
on the stools. Now that could have meant that that was הגבהה.
hagbaha. You caused it to rise up. גמרא Gemara doesn't understand that.
It thinks you're being קונה koneh because it's on your כלי kli
and your כלי kli works as a type of a חצר. chatzer.
So even though it's not in your כלי, kli, it's on your
כלי. kli.
So the גמרא says like this: כמאן
דאמר כלי של לוקח ברשות מוכר קנה לוקח.
keman de-amar
kli
shel loke'ach bi-reshut mocher kana loke'ach. So would you say your vessels
are קונה koneh even in the other person's property because presumably the
elephant was in the original owner's property? So and here it's on
your vessels.
Does that work?
No. הכא במאי עסקינן בסימטא. hacha be-mai askinan be-simta. No, the elephant
is in an alleyway. Okay. So and your כלים kelim worked in
an alleyway. אי נמי, ee nami, or if that doesn't work, בחבילי
זמורות. be-chavilei zemorot. Now that's like, that's like what's that like, climbing
the pipe?
No, well, it
means like bundles of vines. Now רש"י Rashi says what it means
is you make a little bundle and it walks on top of
it. So for רש"י, Rashi, that's, that means that that's like a
type of הגבהה, hagbaha, which is interesting. You didn't physically lift it
up, but you did something to make it rise up. And רש"י
Rashi says it would have to go שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim off
the ground. It's an interesting debate, is הגבהה hagbaha אחד טפח echad
tefach or שלשה טפחים. shelosha tefachim. תוספות Tosafot says a much better
answer. תוספות Tosafot, says no no no, this is elephant food. So
you hang the things high up and it jumps up to get
it and it goes off the ground.
What? Elephants can't jump?
Yeah, I know. תוספות, Tosafot I know, they can be on their
hind legs, but so is that enough that they lift part of
their body off? And the other thing is with תוספות Tosafot, is
that is that it's not clear. In the end,
you didn't physically lift it. You caused it to rise up. How
is that different than causing it to walk on top of something?
Anyway, those are the, you know, so but that is an interesting
debate again, and this is the question about the higher art. Do
we have one minute? We have one minute, so I want to
just read one line of תוספות, Tosafot. which is a hilarious line.
I can't, I still, I learned this when I was like 17
or something and I still can't forget this line in תוספות. Tosafot
There's a question about, let's say you're in a certain type of
a, there's a debate of ראשונים Rishonim in this case. You're in
a certain type of a רשות. reshut. Normally we פסקן, pasken, let's
say we פסקן pasken you know both משיכה meshicha and הגבהה hagbaha
will work. There's a certain approach that well, if you can do
הגבהה, hagbaha, משיכה meshicha won't work. You have to do the better
one. Even if we פסקן pasken both work, if one, if both
are possible, oh this is your room? Okay, fine. Give me 10
seconds. He says you have to do the better one. So תוספות
says, or the רשב"ם Rashbam says: וכי קניינים מצות הן שאין לעשות
אלא מן המובחר? ve-chi kinyanim mitzvot hen she-ein la-asot ella min ha-muvchar?
So, which is like this great line. Anyway, I'll talk about it
more tomorrow. We gotta go. Okay, good to see you guys.